## SARA BLALOCK NG

Department of Linguistics University of Washington Guggenheim Hall Rm. 407-D19 sbng@uw.edu
staff.washington.edu/sbng
github.com/SaraBlalockNg

#### RESEARCH

States of the art in language modeling and related downstream tasks rely on paradigms derived from written language data. My research interest is highlighting what linguistic information is unique to spoken word, and how that can be used to improve computational understanding of natural language. At the University of Washington, I am a member of the Signal, Speech and Language Interpretation (SSLI) Lab in the Department of Electrical Engineering and the Phonetics Lab in the Department of Linguistics.

#### Current Projects:

- Modeling summarizing statistics of prosody across dialogue turns
- Tacit speaker representations of sesquisyllables in English

### Recent Projects:

- Lexical features as predictors of vowel reduction
- Transformers with prosodic cues to detect speech disfluencies in text
- Attitudinal trends in Diaspora Hoisanwa
- Digitizing of narratives in Salish languages (under departmental research assistanceship)

#### EDUCATION

current University of Washington

4th-year Ph.D. student: Computational Linguistics Advised by Drs. Richard Wright and Mari Ostendorf

2013-2017 University of Utah

Honors Bachelor of Arts: Linguistics

Advisor: Dr. Abby Kaplan

Thesis: Musical Text-Setting as Evidence for Syllabification of Highly Moraic Structures in English

Bachelor of Science: Applied Mathematics

**TESOL**: Teaching English to Students of Other Languages Certificate

#### PRESENTATIONS

2018 Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English Linguistic Society of America, with Abby Kaplan and Joselyn Rodriguez

2017 Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns in English
University of Utah Student Conference in Linguistics, with Jenica Jessen & Joselyn Rodriguez
short talk

2017 Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English Undergraduate Research Symposium, University of Utah, with Jenica Jessen poster

#### RESEARCH POSITIONS

2021 US National Institutes of Health, grant NIDCD R01

PI: Richard Wright Research Assistant

2019-2020 US National Science Foundation, grant IIS-1617176

PIs: Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright

Research Assisstant

2019 Google Core Assistant, Pygmalion

Mentor: Katie Vadella

Intern

2017-2018 University of Washington Linguistics

PI: Sharon Hargus

Departmental Research Assistant

#### TEACHING

### **Primary Instructorships**

2020 Summer LING 473: Basics For Computational Linguistics

### Teaching Assistanceships

2020 Fall LING 450: Introduction to Linguistic Phonetics 2019 Spring CSE 472: Introduction to Computational Linguistics

2018 Fall LING 570: Shallow Processing Techniques for Natural Language Processing

2018 Spring LING 269: Swearing and Taboo Language

#### Graderships

2020 Winter LING 451: Phonology I 2019 Spring LING 452: Phonology II 2019 Winter LING 451: Phonology I

#### Curriculum Development

2019 Winter Staff assistanceship converting LING 553 (Experimental Phonetics),

LING 450 (Phonetics), and ASL Program course materials to online format

#### **Guest Lectures**

2019 25 Oct LING 550 (Phonetics I): Reading Spectrograms

2019 21 Aug LING 473 (Compling Basics): Formal Grammars & Parsing

2019 23 May LING 200 (Intro. Linguistics): What is Computational Linguistics?

#### AWARDS

2018 Travel Scholarship for Second Ethics in Natural Language Processing Works	hop	
--	-----	--

North American Chapter of the ACL

2017 Top Scholar Award

University of Washington Graduate School

2017 UROP Small Research Grant

University of Utah Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program

2013 President's Scholarship (full-tuition)

University of Utah

## SERVICE

2020	Editor, University of Washington Working Papers in Linguistics
2020	Student Volunteer, Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
2020	Organizing Committee Member, Northwest Linguistics Conference (NWLC)
2020	Reviewer, NWLC
2020	Proctor, North American Computational Linguistics Open Competition
2020	Consultant, Undergraduate senior capstone in speech translation
2019	President, Linguistics Society of the University of Washington (LSUW)
2019	Student Volunteer, North American Chapter of the ACL
2018	Vice President, LSUW

### SKILLS

## Computer Languages

- $\bullet$  Python (fluent)
- R (fluent)
- HTML/CSS/JavaScript (fluent)
- Java (basic)
- Matlab (basic)

## Machine Learning

- pytorch
- $\bullet$  tensorflow
- Scikit-learn

## Linguistic Tools

- Praat
- NLTK
- Kaldi

## Natural Languages

- French (working)
- Spanish (basic)
- Hoisanwa Chinese (heritage)

# OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

2016-2017 Speech Transcriber, CaptionCall 2014-2017 Mathematics Tutor